Guide to the Susan Christopherson papers, circa 1983-2016.
Christopherson, Susan papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Susan Christopherson papers, circa 1983-2016.
15-2-4300
Susan Christopherson
19.5 cubic feet.
Publications, correspondence, photographs, printed material, reports, manuscripts.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection consists of papers related to Christopherson's research, writing, and teaching.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Susan Christopherson was an economic geographer and Professor and Chair in the Department of City and Regional Planning at Cornell University. Born in St. Paul, Minnesota in 1947, she earned a Bachelor's in Urban Studies and a Master's degree in Geography from the University of Minnesota in 1972 and 1975. After receiving a doctorate in 1983 from the University of California, Berkeley, she was a research associate at the University of California, Los Angeles Graduate School of Architecture and Urban Planning and the Center for U.S.-Mexican Studies at the University of California, San Diego; a visiting professor of geography at San Diego State University; and a visiting lecturer at the University of Texas, El Paso. In 1987, Christopherson joined Cornell's faculty, where she was the first woman promoted to full professor in the Department of City and Regional Planning and, in 2014, became the first woman appointed Chair. Her research and teaching focused on economic development, urban labor markets, and location patterns in media and other service industries. She completed studies on advanced manufacturing in New York's Southern Tier, the photonics industry in Rochester, the role of universities and colleges in revitalizing the upstate New York economy, and production trends affecting media industries in New York City. She also focused on human-environment relations and public policy related to unconventional energy extraction and nontraditional energy sources, analyzing the safety of crude oil transport by rail and the economic consequences of Marcellus shale natural gas drilling. Christopherson co-authored "Remaking Regional Economies: Power, Labor and Firm Strategies in the Knowledge Economy," winner of the 2009 Regional Studies Association Best Book Award, and she published more than 100 articles and policy reports, served on the editorial boards of several leading journals, and was editor-in-chief of a Regional Studies Association book series on cities and regions. At Cornell, she was a faculty fellow in the David R. Atkinson Center for a Sustainable Future. She also consulted with the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development and the United Nations, and she served on a National Research Council panel considering the implications of shale gas and oil development for communities in New York and Pennsylvania. In 2015, she was given a Lifetime Achievement Award by the American Association of Geographers. Christopherson died in 2016.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists of papers related to Christopherson's research, writing, and teaching.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Christopherson, Susan.
Subjects:
Labor mobility -- United States.; Regional economics.; Regional planning.
Places:
New York (State) -- Economic conditions.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Access to folders 38 and 40 in box 2, folder 9 in box 4, folders 32 and 54 in box 6 and folder 7, 36 and 51 in box 19 restricted to the permission of the office of origin.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Series I. Course materials pedagogy
Series II. Series II. Research
Series III. Series III. Produced work
Series IV. Series IV. Correspondence
Series V. Series V. Miscellaneous
Series VI. Seires VI. CRP at Cornell
Series VII. Series VII. Editorial work
Series VIII. Series VIII. Career related
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Course materials pedagogy
  - CRP 417/517 Course Syllabi and Discussions, 1995-2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes course materials for CRP 635 and notes that the course title for 417/517 had changed over time.
  - CRP 417/517 Syllabi for Related Courses, 1994-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes articles and syllabi from other schools.
  - CRP 417/517 Industrial Restructuring and Global Shift Lecture Notes, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes handwritten and typed lectures notes and class exercises.
  - CRP 100 (The American City) Syllabi: 2004, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    NOTE: CRP 100 materials are all from the same box marked "CRP 100 ready for storage" This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100: General"
  - CRP 100 Related Syllabi and Biblio, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100: General"
  - CRP 100: Assignments and Exams, 1998-2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - CRP 100 Mapping Assignment from 1996, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CRP 100 Data Base Assignment from 1996, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - CRP 100: Administrative, 1996-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - CRP 100: The American City, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "Lectures CRP 100 2004"; Contains notes for lectures 1 and 2 as well as offprints and copies of slides or transparencies
  - CRP 100 Lecture Notes, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "Lectures CRP 100 2004"; Contains notes for lectures beginning with week 3
  - CRP 100: Models, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "Lectures CRP 100 2004"; Contains notes and a few articles/clippings about alternative models for city development
  - CRP 100: Immigrants and Cities/Slides, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "Lectures CRP 100 2004"; Contains notes for the lecture on immigration as well as clippings and the transparencies for the lecture
  - CRP 100: 1996 Syllabus, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100 1996"; Contains one copy of the syllabus
  - CRP 100 Lecture 1 Metro Snapshot--Race, Metro-Jobs, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100 1996"; contains lecture notes, overheads, and related materials
  - Urban Geography--Part I--The American Urban System--The Merchant City, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100 1996"; Contains notes for lecture 4 as well as a folder entitled "Urban Geography--Part I--The American Urban System--The Merchant City also notes from J.B. Jackson's Environmental Design course at UC-Berkeley and other materials
  - Urban Policy (marked U Policy), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100 1996"; Contains notes for lecture and a sheet that says "Notes for urban policy talk"--unclear if that is just the lecture or something else
  - CRP 100: Industrial City I, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100 1996"; Contains notes for lecture and an overhead. Note that this was floating loose in the hanging folder and I created a folder for it.
  - Am Cit Lecture--Suburbs, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100 1996"; Contains notes for lectures and a few related readings
  - Overheads for CRP 100, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100 1996"; Contains overheads, including some marked "maybe separate 100 course" and cd-rom marked "CPR 100 American Cities"
  - Lecture Consumption Space and Malls, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100 1996"; Contains notes for lecture, a summary of Sharon Zukin's 'The Culture of Cities,' materials from The Mall of America, and related articles.
  - CRP 100: Miscellaneous Lectures 1996, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100 1996"; Contains typednotes for a John Q. Wilson lecture and a second lecture as well as some hand written notes and a report. Note that this was floating loose in the hanging folder and I created a folder for it.
  - Lectures: Immigration and Urban Models, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100 1996"; Contains overheads, lectures, related readings
  - Lecture: Public Space BIDs (Business Improvement Districts), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100 1996"; Contains slides and related readings, no actual lecture
  - WJ (William Julius) Wilson Lecture notes; Economic Polarization--Bailey and Waldinger, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    This folder is from a hanging file marked "CRP 100 1996"; Contains lectures and related notes
  - CRP 100?, 1996 -2004 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    This is box holding a slide carousel (with slides) that was in the 1996 portion of the "CRP 100: Ready for Storage" file
  - 4170 Readings/Syllabus Fall 2010 (Economic Development), 2010 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Syllabus, a few lecture notes, and other materials related to economic development course
  - Creativity Economy (a.k.a. The Creative Economy) Course Materials, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Contains the syllabus
  - Creative City (a.k.a. The Creative Economy) Course Materials, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Contains notes, lectures, a draft syllabus, to-do list, and other materials relating to the course
  - CRP 417/517 Spring, 2008, 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Contains syllabus, printout of lecture slides, draft slides and final draft text (not for circulation) of Christopherson and Rightor, "Laying the Foundation for a Meaningful Regional Strategic Planning Process, the latter dated Feb. 5, 2007, lecture notes, midterm exam, and other materials relating to the course.
  - Miscellaneous Course Reader Tables of Contents, 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Contains tables of contents taken from four readers, two for CRP 448/548 and two from CRP 550 (Spring 1998, Spring 1999), An Introduction to the Built Environment (Fall, 1990 and n.d)
  - Built Environment and Misc. Syllabi and Ideas, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Contains syllabi, a 1992 memo from Ann Forsyth, various notes and other materials that might or might not be relevant for the Built Environment course.
  - Built Environment Syllabi and Course Proposal, Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Contains syllabi from different iterations of the Built Enviromnent course (CRP 550 and CRP 659-03), notes on revising the class, memos regarding the design and teaching the course, both from 1988 and a later period, as well as various notes related to the course and its design, assignments, etc.
  - The Built Environment Intro, Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Contains lecture notes for the first lectures of the Built Environment course
  - Built Environment Landscape (mythos), Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Contains lecture notes and related readings
  - BE: Vernacular Design, Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Corbusier, 1991-04-02 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Contains lecture notes, copy of slides for lecture (dated 4/2/91)
  - BE: Infrastructure, Undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - BE: Aesthetics in BE; Public Art, Undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Contains a photo of an art installation; copies of 'Law and Aesthetics' by John Costonis, an excerpt from Costonis's book Icons and Aliens were discarded as was the copy of Andreas Huyssen's 'Mapping the Postmodern.' None had marks or notes on them.
  - Built Environment Concluding Remarks, Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Five pages of hand-written notes
  - The Smart Equi[table] City, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Class syllabus and notes for Spring, 2015 2 credit seminar. Also has a description of a special issue on the topic edited by SMC and Amy Glasmeier
  - Planning for Energy Transitions, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Class Syllabus for a CRP special topics course
  - Lectures 417/517, Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Industrial Restructuring 417/517 Lecture 1 Intro to the course, Undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - 417/517 2002, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - AEM 4551 Poverty, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Materials from a course SMC cotaught with Chris Barrett
  - Ideas for Energy Transition Course, Undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Lecture Arch 132, Undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Guest lecture in an architecture course
  - CRP 635 Fall 2002, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Contains only the syllabus
  - Proposals-Pedagogy, Undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Writing Course, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Res Mthd [Research Methods] Course, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Community Economic Development Course Spring 2012, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - CD [Community Development] Course Spring 2012, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - CRP 462 American Planning Tradition, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Contains lecture notes on land use, related syllabi, including one with a note from Roger Trancik thanking SC for helping out in the course, and related readings
  - Gender Issues in Planning Course Materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Contains notes on feminist research methods, a sheet of notes called "Gender Notes," copies of three issues of the Canadian journal 'Women and Environments' and related material.
  - Disliked Land Uses, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Contains a few items related to the topic, including a handout from the 'The New American Ghetto' exhibit at the Storefront Gallery in Soho (NYC) from November/December 1991
  - The Merchant City, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Contains lecture notes, notes on Rochester 1815-1837, a sheet entitled 'Political Implications' and an undated syllabus for CRP 462: American Planning Tradition, folded open to the lecture date.
  - Metropolitan Development, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Contains related syllabi and a few articles relating to metropolitan development
  - Regional Planning: NY, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Contains lecture notes, transparencies and images
  - Fortress City Paper/Talk, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Contains handwritten notes on The Geography of Nowhere, lecture notes entitled "Fortress City-Leccture" that do not look like SC's lecture notes, and a few related items.
  - Security Concerns, Isolation, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Contains a transparency and items related to the topic
  - Housing History, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Contains various pages of notes on Housing (issues/types/history), related materials, personal note from Anthony 'Tony' King dated 16 September 1986 (sent to SMC at UCLA) in which he follows up on having met her recently.
  - Housing Market, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Contains a case study assignment on housing for CRP 550, related materials, and a "very rough draft" of Damaris Rose's 1991 Association of American Geographers (AAG) talk.
  - The New American House, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Contains notes on the house of the future and related materials
  - The European City, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Various articles and materials relating to European cities, some inscribed or with notes, some marked for Built Environment class CRP 659.
  - Future Cities, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Contains notes, list of slides, a transparency of Howard's Garden City model, and a few printouts relating to garden cities
  - CRP 417/517 Lectures 1-3 What's Going On, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Includes lecture notes, transparancies, the typescript of a paper by an unidentified author (may have "Storper" written at the bottom of the page, syllabus for the class, midterm exam, completed application for the University Economic Development Association 2005 Award and related materials
  - Assorted Teaching Related Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Contains a memo about organizing teaching materials, a note inquiring about media-related courses, a short outline of a public policy course, and a hand-written list of courses.
  - CRP 800 Syllabus and Lectures, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Contains lecture notes and syllabus for CRP 800
  - CRP 800 Others' Syllabi, 2000-2004 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Contains syllabi for courses similar to CRP 800 from Ed Soja (2) and Goetz Wolff (2) at UCLA
  - CRP 800 The Regional Critique, Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Contains an article by Allen Scott and a transparency
  - CRP 800 Politics and Practice of Research, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Includes student thesis questions, material from ACSP dissertation workshop (some of which has SMC notes on it)
  - CRP 800 Related Papers from Friends, Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Contains an editorial, Ethics Unbound, by Michael Storper and Andrew Sayer as well as an article by John Forester--both articles have handwritten notes to SMC from the author. These were in a larger hanging folder with the materials for CRP 800. so I created a separate folder for them (PW).
  - CRP 635, Spring, 2006, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Contains material relating to CRP 635--Workshop on State and Local Economic Development Policy: The Environment and Economic Development--including the first page of the syllabus, a note from George Frantz offering to guest lecture (above a course announcement), related syllabi, and notes for the first class
  - CRP 635, Spring, 2006, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Contains materials relating to the class, also a note about the assignment for CRP 417 (misfiled, no doubt)
  - Spring Workshop 635, Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    An overview of "good jobs"-based economic development policies and a list of the 2003 memberhsip and staff of the Central New York Regional Planning and Development Board (based in Syracuse)
  - Planning Education, Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    In a hanging folder entitled "Pedagogy, Liberal Ed"--Contains a handwritten draft of a paper called "Reflections on the Transfer of Intellectual Models from Geography to Planning and on the relationship between Spatial Models and Technocratic Methods Planning" and some papers on planning education
  - Hosting Day Remarks, Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    In a hanging folder entitled "Recruitment, Student"--Contains one disc (entitled Open House Power Point) and one document (author uncertain), entitled Hosting Day Preliminary Remarks that offers a seven page overview of the program. As Barclay Jones is spoken of as on the faculty that might help give a date for it.
  - Mailing Lists, Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    In a hanging folder entitled "Recruitment, Student"--contains a mailing list of programs that received info about CRP as well as related materials including a 3 1/4" disc with CRP Poster
  - Minority, Diversity Recruitment, Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    In a hanging folder entitled "Recruitment, Student"--contains a mailing list of programs called "African American Colleges" that is really a list of African-American faculty like Ed Blakeley and June Thomas.
  - Advisory Council, Undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Contains names of people on advisory council, updates on faculty research in progress and description of the "Re-Thinking Rural Economic Development: A Creative Economy Model
  - Unfiled lecture notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Relates to various economic geography themes
  - Teaching Ideas Web, Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Planning Theory, Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Materials relating to planning theory and its pedagogy--of particular interest an annotated copy of an essay by John Forester on the topic
  - Normative Theory, Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Essays by Susan Fainstein and Sayer/Storper on ethics along with SMC notes on both
  - Green Choices Workshop Readings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Readings with some commentary by SMC
  - CRP 548 and 800--2002-2003, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Syllabi and a few lectures from these courses
  - Books for Urban Theory, Undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Contains notes and a copy of Thomas Hancett's Urban History course at Cornell
  - Urban Theory, 1998-2003 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Contains materials for Spring, 1999 Urban Theory course as well as related syllabi and other materials
  - CRP 519 Urban Theory and Spatial Development, Spring, 2004, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Contains "course annotated bibliographies and discussion synopses." Note that class was cotaught with Matthew Drennan
  - The Global Cities: Their Cities, 2002-09 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Materials relating to lecture about global cities; Includes some student work
    Access restrictions apply.
  - CRP 519: Readins/Syl/Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Notes
  - Papers for Urban Theory, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Various student-submitted discussion notes
  - Lecture Notes :1 The Urban and Regional System, Undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Contains syllabus for CRP 510, lecture notes, overheads, etc.
  - 619 Syllabus, Discussion Questions, Lecture Notes, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    for CRP 619: Introduction to Planning: Theory and Practice--also contains a few things relating to other courses
  - CRP 519 Spring 2003, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Contains material relating to CRP 519 as well as other syllabi and a copy of Kudva and Clavel's 2002 ACSP presentation--"The New Melting Pot: How City Governments Respond to Increasing Diversity"
  - Syllabi for 619, Fall, 1998, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Contains syllabi from similar courses as well as e-mails with comments both Pierre Clavel and Rolf Pendall on a draft syllabus
  - Lecture/Sandercock/Forseyth, Undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Five pages of hand-written notes for a lecture on gender and planning, along with an article by Sandercock and Forseyth on the same
  - Planning Theory/Fischler, Undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Notes on Raphael Fischler's work
  - CRP 519, Undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Notes, syllabi, lecture notes
  - Intro to Course 513, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Notes, syllabi, assignments, lecture notes
  - Electronic Hallway, 1998-2000; FD-699-700 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    A electronic teaching network SMC joined in 1998
  - CRP 448/548 Social Policy and Social Welfare Spring 2006, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Lecture notes, assignments, transparencies and other materials relating to the course
  - Social Justice, Undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Five pages of hand-written notes along with CRP 418/518 discussion question assignment
  - Energy Trans [Transitions] Course, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Fall 2011 Energy Course, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Risk Governence Course, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - 417/517 Spring 2003, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - 417/517 Spring 2004, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Inequality, Diversity and Justice Syllabi, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Copies of the syllabus for a lecture course taught jointly with Richard Miller (Philosophy), Victor Nee (Sociology), Henry Shue (Philosophy/Government/Ethics and Public Life, Steven Shiffrin (Law) along with a letter from Miller inviting Cornell President Hunter Rawlings to come and address the class
  - Other syllabus, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Syllabi from social policy courses along with an e-mail from Richard Miller (7/16/2000) making plans for the Fall
  - 293 Notes, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Notes for lectures, etc. in CRP 293
  - Discussion Q's Midterm, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Discussion questions and midterm, etc., for CRP 448/548
  - Inequality, Diversity, Fall 2000, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    A few readings, transparencies, a note from Ned Rightor with a demographic summary of planet earth
  - Notes on Rose's Stratification (in "Class" folder) Week 3/4, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Contains notes and transparencies for lecture on straitification, as well as notes for a lecture on affirmative action. Likely for CRP 448/548. As mentioned in the title, the folder was in folder on class.
  - 448/548 Syllabi, 1997-2006 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Syllabi for Social Welfare and Social Policy from a number of semesters, sometimes at a graduate level, sometimes undergraduate, including two that were taught at Cornell in Washington
  - CRP 448/548 Course Lists, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Lists of topics and readings